Guide to the John P. Marquand Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John P. Marquand collection
1922-1973
1930-1960
YCAL MSS 48
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.52
(52 boxes)
The John P. Marquand Collection contains manuscripts of books, essays, short stories, addresses, lectures, speeches, and book reviews, as well as business correspondence, research material, bibliographical material, biographical material, and photographic material.
Marquand, John P. (John Phillips), 1893-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was formed from gifts from John P. Marquand, Carol Brandt, and Stephen Birmingham between 1941 and 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN P. MARQUAND (1893-1960)
John Phillips Marquand, leading American writer of the twentieth century, was born on November 10, 1893, to Philip and Margaret Fuller Marquand, both descendants of old New England families. Although he was born in Wilmington, Delaware, and lived in Rye, New York, until he was fourteen, Marquand considered himself a New Englander. He was educated at the Newburyport (Massachusetts) High School and at Harvard University, from which he was graduated in 1915. From 1915 to 1917, he was assistant magazine editor of the Boston Transcript. After a brief period as advertising copywriter in 1920 and 1921, he became a novelist and published The Unspeakable Gentleman (1922). Marquand was a frequent contributor of short stories to several popular magazines of the day, most notably The Saturday Evening Post, Cosmopolitan, Collier's, and Good Housekeeping. Many of his novels were also serialized in shortened form in these magazines.
A recurring theme in many of Marquand's works concerns the life and times of the middle and upper classes in twentieth-century New England--particularly Boston--as illustrated in The Late George Apley (1937), Wickford Point (1939), and H. M. Pulham, Esquire (1941). Marquand also wrote several mysteries featuring the Oriental detective Mr. Moto. Film versions of the Mr. Moto mysteries enjoyed great popularity. Marquand's writings were widely received and sold well. In addition, many of his works were successfully adapted for stage and screen.
In 1922, Marquand married Christina Sedgwick. From this marriage, which lasted thirteen years, a son and a daughter were born. In 1936, Marquand married Adelaide Hooker. Two sons and a daughter were born of this union, which also ended in divorce in 1958.
John P. Marquand died in his sleep of a heart attack on July 16, 1960 in Newburyport, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The John P. Marquand Collection contains manuscripts of books, essays, short stories, addresses, lectures, speeches, and book reviews, as well as business correspondence, research material, biliographical material, biographical material, and photographic material that document the life and career of John P. Marquand. The material spans the years 1922 to 1973, with the bulk falling between 1930 and 1960.
The papers are housed in fifty-two boxes and are divided into three series. The John P. Marquand Papers are by far the largest series in the collection. Brandt & Brandt Papers and Stephen Birmingham Papers make up the rest of the collection. Oversize material is placed at the end.
Yale acquired Marquand's manuscripts in Series I through the intervention of Wilmarth S. Lewis, a 1918 graduate of Yale and generous benefactor to his alma mater. Lewis was reading H. M. Pulham, Esquire when he came upon the passage where Harry Pulham was returning from New York to Boston at the time his father was dying. He had been working for a tough westerner in the advertising business and the western friend was with him. When they got off the train in New Haven to smoke a cigarette, the western friend said "You know, I have always really thought you should have been a Yale man," which shocked Pulham. At this moment Lewis sat down and wrote Marquand a note, and asked him if he would consider giving the manuscript of that novel to Yale. Box 5, folder 93 contains Marquand's reply to Lewis's request. Over the next twenty years practically all of Marquand's literary manuscripts were transferred to Yale.
Series I, John P. Marquand Papers (Boxes 1-37), covers the period 1924-59 and is divided into two subseries: Books and Shorter Works. The Books subseries contains drafts for the majority of Marquand's book-length works, from his first novel, The Unspeakable Gentleman (1922) to his last, Timothy Dexter, Revisited (1960). Marquand's reputation as a novelist was made with The Late George Apley (1937), a Pulitzer Prize winner which was later made into a play and film. Drafts for both the novel and the play are found in Boxes 6-8. Occasionally there is correspondence relating to specific book titles between Marquand or his literary agents and publishers. Box 8, folder 159 contains correspondence between Marquand and George S. Kaufman, who collaborated with the author in adapting The Late George Apley for the stage.
Research material for Prince and Boatswain (1915), Marquand's first literary publication, is found in Box 17, folders 341-42. The inscrutable Mr. Moto, Marquand's mystery crime solver, is represented by Mercator Island (1942) and Mr. Moto Is So Sorry (1938). Other major works include B. F.'s Daughter (1946), H. M. Pulham, Esquire (1941), Melville Goodwin, USA (1951), Point of No Return (1949), Sincerely, Willis Wayde (1955), Wickford Point (1939), and Women and Thomas Harrow (1958). A number of these works appeared first in serial form in popular magazines such as The Saturday Evening Post and Collier's before they were published in book form. Occasionally the serialized version appeared under a title different than the published title. Last Laugh, Mr. Moto (1942), for instance, was first published in Collier's as Mercator Island.
The next subseries, Shorter Works, is divided into five section: Essays and Short Stories; Addresses, Lectures, and Speeches; Book Reviews; Letters to the Editor; and Contributions to Works of Others. Essays and Shorts Stories primarily represent drafts of Marquand's shorter works published in magazines. Addresses, Lectures, and Speeches constitute drafts of his public-speaking engagements, a considerable number of which are found under the headings Harvard University speeches and Tuesday Night Club papers. The Tuesday Night Club was a literary institution in Newburyport, Massachusetts. Marquand took his membership in this organization quite seriously and worked on these papers with as much care and diligence as he did on his novels. The remainder of the subseries is made up of book reviews, letters to the editor, and contributions to works of others.
Marquand discovered relatively early in his career that he worked best by dictating his ideas directly to his secretary in the mornings and correcting the typed copy in the afternoons. Consequently, there are very few holograph drafts in the collection.
Series II, Brandt & Brandt Papers (Boxes 38-43), provides insight into the professional aspects of John P. Marquand's career, as they represent information generated and/or collected by Brandt & Brandt, his literary agents. These papers were donated to the Beinecke Library by Carol Brandt in the 1960s and early '70s. They cover the period 1922-70 and are divided into three subseries: Business Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. Business Correspondence consists of four boxes of letters of Marquand, Carl and Carol Brandt, and magazine editors, publishers, and film agents and producers between 1948 and 1970. Representative correspondents include: Harry Sions of Holiday, G. M. White and Alice Conkling of Ladies' Home Journal, Andrew Crichton of Sports Illustrated, William Jay Gold of Life, Stuart Rose of The Saturday Evening Post, Alfred McIntyre and Cammann Newberry of Little, Brown & Company, Ray Stark, Hollywood film agent, and the law offices of Margulies & Heit. Topics discussed include: negotiations concerning publication of short stories and novels, payments and royalties, film adaptations, suggested story topics, and legal issues relating to publication. Writings primarily contains advertisements, book reviews, and synopses of Marquand's books as well as printed versions of essays and short stories collected by the Brandt & Brandt office. Other Papers is composed of bibliographical material, biographical material, photographic negatives, and works on Marquand. Box 43, folders 957-58 contain a published bibliography of Marquand's works compiled by Professor William White in 1949-50.
Series III, Stephen Birmingham Papers (Boxes 44-49), consists of the working papers and drafts of Stephen Birmingham's biography of John P. Marquand. Early in his writing career, Birmingham chose Brandt & Brandt as his literary agents, who later introduced him to John Marquand a few years before his death. These papers reveal the close working relationship between Birmingham and Carol Brandt in the late 1960s and early '70s during which time Birmingham was working on the biography. Much of the research material was, in fact, given to Birmingham by Carol Brandt, along with material from other close friends of Marquand. In the early 1970s Birmingham donated the papers to the Beinecke Library.
The papers cover the period 1930-73 and are divided into five subseries: Research Material, Interviews, The Late John Marquand, Photographs, and Business Correspondence. Research Material is made up of files on individuals and consists primarily of correspondence, notes, and character sketches. Prominent individuals in this subseries include: Stephen Birmingham, Charles B. Blanchard, Carl and Carol Brandt, Constance Fiske, Robert Hale, Charles and Anne Lindbergh, Adelaide and John Marquand, Herbert R. Mayes, Cammann Newberry, Stuart Rose, Harry Sions, Ray Stark, and King Vidor. Most of the correspondence in this subseries provides some kind of biographical information about Marquand. Interviews is composed of transcriptions, notes, and cassette tapes of interviews with Carol Brandt and King Vidor by Stephen Birmingham. The Late John Marquand consists of the drafts of Birmingham's biography, advertisements, publicity, book reviews, and fan mail. Illustrations used in the book are found in the Photographs subseries. Business Correspondence is made up primarily of letters between Birmingham and Carol Brandt and reveals her collabration with the author on this project. These letters contain anecdotes and other information used in the biography. One interesting aspect covered in this series is the battle between Marquand's children by his first wife, John P. Marquand, Jr. and Christina ("Tina") Marquand Welch, and Birmingham. Johnny and Tina were strongly opposed to Birmingham's biography. Birmingham was supported, however, by Carol Brandt and other friends of Marquand, such as Conney Fiske. The authorized biography was written by Millicent Bell of Boston University. Box 49, folder 1073d contains an exchange of letters between Christina Marquand Welch and Stephen Birmingham in which they express their feelings of opposition to the other's position following the publication of The Late John Marquand.
The Oversize section contains primarily printed versions of Marquand's book serializations, essays, and short stories, as they appeared in various popular magazines from the Brandt & Brandt Papers.
Authors and publishers; Authors, American -- Biography; Boston (Mass.) -- History -- Fiction; Massachusetts -- History -- Fiction; New England -- History -- Fiction; Newburyport (Mass.) -- History -- Fiction; United States -- History -- Fiction; Authors -- Massachusetts; Literary agents -- United States; Birmingham, Stephen, 1929-2015; Brandt, Carl; Brandt, C. (Carol); Fiske, Constance; Marquand, Adelaide Ferry Hooker; Marquand, Christina Sedgwick, 1897-1951; Marquand, John P. (John Phillips), 1893-1960; Brandt & Brandt
- John P. Marquand Papers, 1924-59; Series I; 15.25; (37 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The John P. Marquand Papers consist of manuscript drafts of the author's books, essays, short stories, addresses, lectures, speeches, book reviews, and contributions to the works of others. The papers also contain correspondence, synopses, and galley proofs for some works.
  - BOOKS
    - B. F.'s Daughter
      - Draft A, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22-32)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33-37)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38-45)
      - Correspondence, 1945-46 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - The Black Cargo
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47-52)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - H. M. Pulham, Esquire
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 54-59)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60-68)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70-75)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 76-77)
      - Galley proofs, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78-92)
      - Correspondence, 1941 Mar 12 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Haven's End
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 94-97)
    - It's Loaded, Mr. Bauer
      - Draft, typescript, carbon, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 98-101)
    - Last Laugh, Mr. Moto
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Mercator Island, Box 13, folder 257
    - The Late George Apley
      - Novel
        - Draft A, typescript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 102-03)
        - Draft A, typescript, carbon and original (Box 6, Folder 104-08)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 109-17)
        - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 118-24)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 125-31)
        - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 132)
      - Play
        Prologue
        - Draft A, typescript, carbon, corrected (incomplete), 1944 Mar 6 (Box 7, Folder 133)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, 1944 Mar 6 (Box 7, Folder 134)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 135)
        - Draft D, typescript, carbon, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 136)
        - Prologue and Act One: draft, typescript, corrected, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 137)
        - Act One
          - Draft A, typescript, carbon (incomplete), 1944 (Box 8, Folder 138)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1944 Mar 23 (Box 8, Folder 139-40)
          - Draft C, typescript, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 141)
        - Act Two
          - Draft A, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 142-43)
          - Draft B, typescript, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 144)
          - Draft fragments, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 145-46)
        - Act Three
          - Synopsis, typescript, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 147)
          - Draft, typescript, carbon, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 148-49)
          - Draft fragments, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 150)
        - Complete Drafts
          - Draft A, typescript, carbon, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 151-52)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 153-55)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 156-58)
        - Correspondence, 1942, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 159)
    - Life at Happy Knoll
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 160)
      - "Are Women People at Happy Knoll?": draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 161)
      - "Breakfast at Happy Knoll"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 162)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 163)
      - "Consistency at Happy Knoll"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 164)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 165)
      - "Deficit at Happy Knoll": draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 166)
      - "Happy Knoll Never Competes"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 167)
        - Draft A, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 168)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 169)
      - "How Short Are Shorts at Happy Knoll?"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 170)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 171)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 172)
      - "Locker Room Trouble at Happy Knoll"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 173)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 174)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 175)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 176)
      - "Semantics at Happy Knoll"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 177)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 178)
      - "Should Old Acquaintance Be Forgot?"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 179)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 180)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 181)
      - "That's the Way the Ball Bounces"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 182)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 183)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 184)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 185)
      - Unidentified manuscripts
        - No. 1: draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 186)
        - No. 2: draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 187)
        - No. 3: draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 188)
        - No. 3: draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 189)
    - Lord Timothy Dexter
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 190-91)
      - Draft, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 192-95)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 196)
    - Melville Goodwin, USA
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 197-200)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 201-17)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 218-23)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 224-36)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 237-44)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 245-56)
    - Mercator Island
      - Draft A, typescript, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 257-61)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 262-65)
    - Mr. Moto Is So Sorry
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 266-72)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 273-77)
      - Draft B, corrected pages, typescript, carbon, 1938 Feb 16 (Box 13, Folder 278)
    - Point of No Return
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 279-81)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 282-98)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 299-304)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 305-17)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 318-22)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 323-34)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 335-37)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 338-40)
    - Prince and Boatswain
      - Research material, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 341-42)
    - Repent in Haste
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 343-46)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 347-50)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 351-54)
      - Draft C, typescript, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 355-56)
      - Draft C, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 357-58)
    - Sincerely, Willis Wayde
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 359)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 360-76)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 377-80)
      - Draft A, first half (before revision), typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 381-91)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 392-95)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 396-407)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 408-16)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 417-20)
      - Draft C, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 421-33)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 434-35)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 436-39)
      - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 440)
    - So Little Time
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 441-56)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 457-61)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 462-75)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 476-89)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 490-97)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 498-501)
      - Correspondence, 1942-43 (Box 25, Folder 502)
    - Stopover Tokyo
      - Draft A, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 503-09)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 510-16)
    - Thirty Years
      - "Foreword": draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 517)
    - Three Three Eight
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 518-21)
    - Timothy Dexter Revisited
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 522-29)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 530-34)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 535-39)
    - Two If By Sea
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 540-44)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 545)
    - The Unspeakable Gentleman
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 546-48)
      - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 549)
    - Wickford Point
      - Novel
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 550-56)
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 557-62)
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 28, Folder 563-69)
        - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 570-77)
        - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 578-80)
        - Draft C, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 581-91)
        - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 592)
      - Radio Dramatization
        - Scene-plot, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 593)
        - Dramatization, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 594)
    - Women and Thomas Harrow
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 595-98)
      - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 599-614)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 615-17)
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 618-35)
      - Draft C, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 636-47)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - Essays and Short Stories
      See also: Box 34-36, folders 701-777; Oversize, Boxes 50 and 51
      - "American Crude"
        - Draft, typescript, carbon, 1937 (Box 32, Folder 648-51)
        - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 32, Folder 652)
      - "Are the Chinese People?": draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 653)
      - "Beginning Now": draft, typescript, carbons, 1939 Sep (Box 32, Folder 654)
      - "The Big Guys": draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 655)
      - Boston Herald--Cunningham column, Article for: draft, typescript, carbon, 1950 Sep (Box 32, Folder 656)
      - "The Breath of a Hair": draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 657)
      - "Cambodia"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 658)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 659)